<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference on Arnaud Bos</title>
    <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conference on Arnaud Bos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 22:56:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ClojuTRE &amp; SmallFP 2018 — Review</title>
      <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/clojutre-finland-2018-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 22:56:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/clojutre-finland-2018-review/</guid>
      <description>Helsinki    ClojuTRE is a Clojure conference happening in Finland since 2012.
I was super eager to attend a Clojure conference this year, so the addition of SmallFP just before ClojuTRE finally amortized the travel cost.
tl;dr   SmallFP did deliver a great experience by allowing an audience of Clojure developers to hear about other functional programming languages and concepts.
  The topics were a nice mixture of industry practices, libraries and research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>J On The Beach 2018 — Review</title>
      <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-malaga-2018-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 23:12:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-malaga-2018-review/</guid>
      <description>360 Photo — Plaza del Obispo    J On The Beach (JOTB) is &amp;ldquo;A Big Data Conference On The Beach&amp;rdquo; happening in Malaga (Spain) and this year (2018) was its third edition.
tl;dr   The staff was great, the speakers awesome and the talks interesting.
  I felt very comfortable and almost at home during the three days. The atmosphere felt like being at a local conference or meetup but with famous and renowned speakers from around the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>J On The Beach 2017 — Review</title>
      <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-malaga-2017-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 16:23:15 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-malaga-2017-review/</guid>
      <description>Panoramic view — Seaside of Malaga — Hiking the day after the conference    J On The Beach (JOTB) is &amp;ldquo;A Big Data Conference On The Beach&amp;rdquo; happening in Malaga (Spain) and this year (2017) was its second edition.
tl;dr   The staff was great, the speakers awesome and the talks interesting.
  I felt very comfortable and almost at home during the three days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>J On The Beach 2017 — Jepsen Workshop</title>
      <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-jepsen-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:23:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/j-on-the-beach-jepsen-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Network&amp;#39;s Laggy     Store it maybe    Photos shamelessly stolen from Kyle Kinsburry&amp;#39;s website   The first book I&amp;rsquo;ve read about distributed systems was Distributed Systems: Principles and Paradigms by Andrew S. Tanenbaum and Maarten van Steen.
I was reading at the library on my last year of study and I remember being confused very often, and to be honest I didn&amp;rsquo;t even finish it&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EclipseCon France 2016 — Review</title>
      <link>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/eclipsecon-france-2016-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 12:55:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://i-rant.arnaudbos.com/eclipsecon-france-2016-review/</guid>
      <description>Keynote    This ear, I&amp;rsquo;ve been given the opportunity to attend the French edition of the EclipseCon. It&amp;rsquo;s been the first time I could attend an event of this nature with Keynotes, workshops, talks and demos on various topics, informal talks with other attendees and speakers.
Bellow is a feedback on my experience of the EclipseCon France 2016.
Schedule: https://www.eclipsecon.org/france2016/conference/schedule/session/2016-06-07
 Connecting low power IoT devices with LoRa, MQTT, and The Things Network  From my point of view, IoT really was an important topic this year in Toulouse, most notably because of the presence of The Things Network, who&amp;rsquo;s been invited by the Eclipse Foundation to lead a workshop and give the first Keynote of the conference.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>